A Guide to the Papers of Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble 1951-1973
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
The Papers of Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble 1951-1973
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-16
The collection consists of 1 box: 13 cm x 39.5 cm x 26. 5 cm of processed materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired with the Papers of Edward W. Hook.
Biographical/Historical Information
Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble was born on May 8, 1900 in Charlottesville, Virginia. On October 19, 1925, she married Henry Bearden Mulholland, a premier professor of internal medicine at the University of Virginia from 1920-1966. Together they had two children, Elizabeth and Jack. Following Mulholland's death, Elizabeth married Edward W. Gamble Jr. in 1968. She died March 15, 2001 at the age of 101 in a nursing home in Maryland.
For over six decades, Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble was exceedingly active in volunteer efforts for the University, the medical school, and hospital. She used her talents to improve UVa's clinical and educational facilities and enhance services to patients and their families. Her most significant accomplishment was to establish the Pink Lady Services Organization in 1951. By Gamble's own accounts, she raised over $90,000 for medical departments which included the purchases of the first cobalt machine, the first electron microscope, two specially equipped vans to test children for deafness in public schools throughout Virginia, and funds for landscaping of the Children's Rehabilitation Center. Gamble was also a passionate tennis player. She wrote her autobiography in 1974 and titled it "She Dares to Be Different."
Scope and Content
The Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble collection includes correspondence to and from Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble. Also included are a Woman's Hospital Auxiliary Badge and two photographs.
Box 18, Folder 11 located in the Papers of Edward W. Hook deal with the dedication of a courtyard garden at the University of Virginia Hospital in her honor. Historical Collections & Services houses a complementary collection, University of Virginia Hospital Auxiliary Collection (Hospital Circle) 1908-2003, MS-13, which details Gamble's (as Mrs. Mulholland) involvement in this organization.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by date.
Contents List
- Dixie Hospital Auxiliary [n.d.], 1 TD w AN (Box-folder 001-001)
  Gamble began hospital auxiliaries in Hampton, Waynesboro, Front Royal, and Harrisonburg.
- Artifact: Women's Hospital Auxiliary Badge [n.d.], 1 Artifact (Box-folder 001-002)
- Photograph: Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble [n.d.], 1 photograph (Box-folder 001-003)
- Photograph: "The First Days of the Pink Lady Canteen" 1951, 1 photograph (Box-folder 001-004)
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Thomas H. Hunter, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-005)
  Hunter thanks Gamble for her work in the Medical School and Hospital and for organizing student wives' meetings.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from John M. Stacey February 13, 1954, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-006)
  Stacey hunts for a replacement for Gamble in organizing the cart service and the canteen.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from John M. Stacey February 20, 1954, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-007)
  Stacey would like to organize a tea in Gamble's honor for her volunteer service.
- Program: Fifth Annual Meeting of the Va. Association of Women's Hospital Auxiliaries April 13-14, 1954, 1 TD (Box-folder 001-008)
  Gamble gives a speech, "Services Found Most Successful and Applicable to Large and Small Hospitals."
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Colgate W. Darden, Jr. December 3, 1955, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-009)
  Darden mentions possibly providing equipment from monies at his disposal and briefly mentions the tennis courts. Gamble writes comments about his statements.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from George Cooper, Jr., M.D. April 19, 1955, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-010)
  Cooper is thrilled to have Gamble as an ally to reach his goal of acquiring a [cobalt machine.]
- Letter to the Trustees of the University of Virginia Alumni fund from Elizabeth Brown Mulholland June 7, 1955, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-011)
  Gamble expresses concern about tennis conditions at UVa.
- Letter to George Eager from Allan T. Gwathmey June 7, 1955, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-012)
  Equipment needed for the Department of Chemistry includes a Carl Zeiss Stereo Microscope and an Exacta VX.
- Letter to Allan T. Gwathmey from George Eager June 15, 1955, 1 TL (Box-folder 001-013)
  Eager assures Gwathmey that efforts will be made to obtain funding for the needs of Cobb Chemical Lab.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Mortimer M. Caplin October 3, 1955, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-014)
  Caplin comments on the tennis conditions at UVa; Gamble responds in handwritten notes.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Joseph Vining April 4, [n.d.], 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-015)
  Vining attempts to raise money for a Hungarian "freedom fighter" to attend UVa.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from [Mrs. Jack Rinehart] [n.d.], 1 ALS (Box-folder 001-016)
  Gamble is asked to consider chairing the meeting of the Garden Club of Virginia in May 1956.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Ladley Husted February 22, 1956, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-017)
  The Department of Biology wants to purchase a Circular Barcroft-Warburg apparatus. Gamble writes in the margins that she raised $1,200 to secure this purchase.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from William H. Mueller, Jr. March 16, 1956, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-018)
  Mueller thanks Gamble for obtaining the money to purchase a defibrillator for the Department of Surgery.
- Letter to Fletcher D. Woodward from [s.n.] Hydl April 20, 1956, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-019)
  Gamble & Woodward's request for a purchase of a station wagon for the Virginia Hearing Foundation was approved.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from the Secretary to Drs. Archer & Cooper August 6, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-020)
  Gamble established the Lahey Fund.
- Letter to George Eager from Elizabeth Brown Mulholland October 8, 1956, 2 TL (Box-folder 001-021)
  Gamble provides a report of all her volunteer work. She estimates she raised around $90,000 for purchases such a cobalt machine, microscopes, defibrillator, and a Ford mobile unit.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Thomas H. Hunter October 10, 1956, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-022)
  Hunter thanks Gamble for her annual report.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Oscar A. Thorup, Jr. February 27, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-023)
  Thorup requests Gamble's aid in soliciting money to help send 3 students to work at a London hospital during the summer. Gamble writes she was able to send them, but had to sell box bushes and box lunches to meet the final needs.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Mary Wendt [n.d.], 1 ALS (Box-folder 001-024)
  Wendt sends $500 to sponsor a student to England.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Thomas H. Hunter March 25, 1957, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-025)
  Hunter thanks Gamble for her assistance in sending students to England.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from William H. Muller, Jr. April 17, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-026)
  Muller requests funds to purchase a cardiac machine.
- Letter to Mr. & Mrs. Richard Stockham from George Cooper, Jr. May 10, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-027)
  The Stockham's, friends of Gamble, donated money to purchase equipment for the Isotope Laboratory.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from C. Bruce Morton II May 20, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-028)
  Gamble raised money by hosting a lunch and garden tour at Albemarle homes.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Thomas H. Hunter August 9, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-029)
  Hunter thanks Gamble for her good works.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from James M. Mullendore September 10, 1957, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-030)
  Gamble writes she was able to secure a station wagon for the Speech and Hearing Center and then a second one when the first was worn out.
- Letter to W. E. Lindsay from C.W. Hendryx November 15, 1957, 1 TL (Box-folder 001-031)
  Hendryx thanks Lindsay for the boxwood for the Children's Rehabilitation Center.
- Letter to Hank [Henry Bearden Mulholland] from Richard James Stockham December 9, 1957, 1 AL (Box-folder 001-032)
  Stockton sends a $1,000 check for Gamble to use for Medical College projects.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Louisa K. Cochran November 10, 1958, 1 TLS w AN (Box-folder 001-033)
  Cochran thanks Gamble for her involvement in a reception.
- Letter to Hank [Henry Bearden Mulholland] and Elizabeth [Brown Mulholland] from [Richard James Stockham] [n.d.], 1 AL (Box-folder 001-034)
  Stockham has confidence that Gamble will use his $1000 donation appropriately.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland from Richard James Stockham February 1, 1958, 1 ALS (Box-folder 001-035)
  Stockham donates $2,000 towards Gamble's good works.
- Pamphlet: "Bazaar News for St. Paul's Church" [November] 1972, 1 TD (Box-folder 001-036)
  Gamble serves as the 1972 Bazaar chairman.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble from David Ward November 22, 1972, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-037)
  Ward thanks Gamble for her work at the bazaar.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble from Elizabeth B. Gleason January 24, 1973, 1 TL (Box-folder 001-038)
  Gleason thanks Gamble for her tremendous contribution in the success of St. Paul's bazaar.
- Letter to Mrs. Jarman from Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble November 10, 1[9]73, 1 TLS (Box-folder 001-039)
  Gamble discusses her role in developing the Pink Ladies.
- Letter to Elizabeth Brown Mulholland Gamble from Lucy Bleecker [n.d.], 1 ALS (Box-folder 001-040)
  Bleecker thanks Gamble for her involvement in the benefit for Albemarle Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals.